<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-12T01:21:01+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">rishi raj’s blog</title><subtitle>On work, marketing and the service industry. Also, rants about management and development processes.
</subtitle><author><name>Rishi Raj</name></author><entry><title type="html">Sonos and 5 GHz Wi-Fi Connections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/sonos-5ghz-wifi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sonos and 5 GHz Wi-Fi Connections" /><published>2023-12-30T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-12-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/sonos-5ghz-wifi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/sonos-5ghz-wifi">&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to share a recent experience I had with my new Sonos Era 100 speaker – a device that truly exceeded my expectations in terms of sound quality and design. However, the setup process wasn’t as smooth as I anticipated, especially when it came to connecting the speaker to my Wi-Fi network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge: Connecting to 5GHz Wi-Fi&lt;/strong&gt;
I hit a snag. When I tried to set up the speaker using the Sonos app, I noticed that my 5GHz network wasn’t listed among the available Wi-Fi networks. Oddly enough, the 2.4GHz network appeared just fine. This was puzzling because media devices generally perform better on 5GHz networks due to their higher bandwidth capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research: Understanding Wi-Fi Channels&lt;/strong&gt;
Determined to resolve this issue, I dived into some research. I learned that Wi-Fi networks operate on various channels, and these channels can affect the connectivity of devices. Specifically, the 5GHz band has a range of channels, and not all devices are compatible with every channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the Sonos works best on certain channels within the 5GHz band, particularly Channel 44. This was a revelation because my router was set to ‘Auto’ for channel selection, meaning it could have been using a channel incompatible with my Sonos speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution: Manual Channel Adjustment&lt;/strong&gt;
The solution was clear: I needed to manually set my router to use Channel 44 on the 5GHz band. After accessing my router’s settings and making this adjustment, I attempted to connect my Sonos speaker again. This time, it worked flawlessly! The speaker connected to the 5GHz network without any further issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion: A Happy Ending&lt;/strong&gt;
Now, my Sonos Era 100 is up and running on the 5GHz network, delivering the high-quality audio experience I was looking forward to. This experience taught me the importance of understanding the technical aspects of Wi-Fi networks, especially when setting up smart home devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re facing similar issues with your Wi-Fi-connected devices, remember to check your router’s channel settings. Sometimes, a simple tweak is all it takes to ensure a smooth, seamless connection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Raj</name></author><category term="python" /><summary type="html">Today, I want to share a recent experience I had with my new Sonos Era 100 speaker – a device that truly exceeded my expectations in terms of sound quality and design. However, the setup process wasn’t as smooth as I anticipated, especially when it came to connecting the speaker to my Wi-Fi network.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Self-Trust Rant</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/the-self-trust-rant" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Self-Trust Rant" /><published>2018-04-21T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-04-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/the-self-trust-rant</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/the-self-trust-rant">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Trust yourself, you know more than you think you do. - Benjamin Spock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the quoted/misquoted quotes, global personalities, superheroes and everyday lore you hear, guide all its energy to one thing; this estranged character on which our civilization thrives:  &lt;em&gt;making an attempt, give it a try&lt;/em&gt;. Whether the certainty of the outcome is known, predictable or unknown, the effort of “trying” to do something is always compared to its direct outcome; necessarily a positive one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.licdn.com/dms/image/C5112AQFaNJCUt_vzxA/article-cover_image-shrink_720_1280/0/1524330042897?e=1709164800&amp;amp;v=beta&amp;amp;t=u_2-tbmxDgPliP3Oq3adLn21KY3vffoLNX8mi4522jg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the much #HUSTLE hype, everyone is trying to do a lot of things and many of them are doing his or her thing really well. Now, let’s not only stick to an entrepreneur as the doers here. There is a huge, huge population which makes it to their work every day (be it an advertising executive or a plumber) and they “try” their day’s best to do things they are supposed to do. As part of the popular culture, they are expected, each one of them; to set &amp;amp; break benchmarks, become stars of their function, use time as vitamins, do their work with an unmatched zeal and be indispensable. But we all aren’t the most productive and ROI optimized in our actions. Therefore, a huge part of this huge, huge population ends up under-delivering the expected while overloading on the byproducts: disinterest, boredom and, lack of conscious respect for one’s own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So what is going wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many things. But I’d like to mention one, a special low hanging fruit called Self-Trust and its retrospective in what we do. Often used as words like Belief, Hope and Confidence, in all its etymology the best &amp;amp; perhaps most important aspect of them come up when a prefix “Self-” is added in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Self Trust is a major miss today and hence, an alarmingly important ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These misses are there because of the competitive nature of our environment and, the lack of a conscious pass-over at work or home. Also, Hollywood (no movie rants ahead). If asked about one’s confidence in everything they do in their 9-to-5 (or, 11-to-8), the common answers that pop up are,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is there, somewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;None whatsoever. What I do is meaningless to me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is there, lots of it; jacking up for the “special work” from the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My manager takes decision for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The underlying purpose of one’s work becomes so subliminal to their own eyes, that they don’t see their own effort’s value, trusted actions and, consider placing their belief in the smaller things too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in recent times, people have moved mountains with Self Trust in our Work. A great example of it is Elon Musk. The technology maverick has not always been the favourite poster child for the “entrepreneurial spirit”. In fact, both of his flagship companies Tesla Motors and SpaceX have seen miserable times. There was a certain time when all of Elon’s fortune was invested deep into his two companies. However, despite all that came, Elon had a strong trust in himself, why he wanted to do what he’s doing (to eradicate the use of fossil fuels from Earth) and an unshaken trust in what he was doing (building cars and spaceships). The energy this self-trust induced had a team-level impact on Tesla and SpaceX. Not only all of his teams believed in what they were doing and trusted the methods they were trying. It gave Elon a leadership splurge like no other. This was, of course, followed by the public’s trust in Elon and his companies. Don’t you love what he’s doing with Tesla or SpaceX?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’d also want to quote Steve Jobs on this, but that’ll be too much of a cliche to handle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what needs to be done? If there is no visible trust in oneself &amp;amp; one’s work, it has been brought around by people surrounding this person — friends, family, coworkers. Showing gratitude and letting people know that you trust them with their work, process and method is the biggest cultural gateway a company can move towards. While it may look difficult for a larger organization, smaller ones can start nurturing this exercise, in their contained environment on conversations. Moreover, as individuals, we should be consciously aware of what we are doing and why we are doing it to sustain, well, trust in ourselves. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Raj</name></author><category term="python" /><summary type="html">Trust yourself, you know more than you think you do. - Benjamin Spock</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Handheld to Handworn: Are you ready for it?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/handheld-to-handworn-devices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Handheld to Handworn: Are you ready for it?" /><published>2018-01-05T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-01-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/handheld-to-handworn-devices</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/handheld-to-handworn-devices">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.licdn.com/dms/image/C5612AQGpySQToEkMSw/article-cover_image-shrink_720_1280/0/1520172827017?e=1709164800&amp;amp;v=beta&amp;amp;t=WOnV-qk0JVsbE8tbsQcmhMy4vF-KAnqbURySuQSu4aw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Apple announced the Watch Series 3, it made a significant push, inching a milestone that might just reshape the personal devices universe. Apple achieved what was previously unimaginable: creating a hand-worn device that operates independently from its handheld counterpart. In fact, some regarded 4G in the Watch as Apple’s most significant announcement in 2017, bigger than the iPhone X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although smartphones, used by over a billion people globally, may still be considered the most personal device type on the market, the undeniable global surge in the wearables market cannot be ignored. This trend began with fitness as the primary focus for wearable devices, which then evolved into companions for smartphones. However, wearables are poised to replace smartphones as the primary personal devices for consuming and sharing information, functioning independently without needing another device as a connectivity conduit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings up the question: As a developer, designer, content producer, or marketer, are you ready for this change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a marketer, I recognize mobile as a focal point in my industry. From the usability of products to avenues of advertising, mobile is leading the trends chart. Short-lived or not, this trend will evolve in itself; just like the screens on these mobiles. Back in 2013, screen fragmentation was the primary concern among the mobile concentrating community. It took four years and a leap of faith from manufacturers to standardize the process and put an end to this concern. Today, the same fragmentation is taking birth for devices in the ‘hands’ category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tap well &amp;amp; early, hand-worn devices or the wearables segment is to be taken seriously starting 2018. They should be viewed as independent devices, heralding entirely new consumer behaviors across various processes and cycles. For marketers like me, it even calls to reinvent mobile advertising as we know it, with new communication methods and units. Wearables like the Apple Watch are already fostering an ecosystem of apps and unique options designed exclusively for them. From locating your car in a parking lot or booking an Uber, to making reservations at your favorite restaurant, all these tasks are now possible directly from your wrist-worn device, without the need to unlock your smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your thoughts: Will 2018 be the year when wearables emerge as devices to be taken seriously and considered individually, and not just as companion machines to smartphones?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Raj</name></author><category term="python" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automating the Attendance Module at Work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/managing-djangos-settings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automating the Attendance Module at Work" /><published>2014-09-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-09-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/managing-djangos-settings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/managing-djangos-settings">&lt;p&gt;This place I work has an online portal where every employee must login with their user credentials and log their attendance for the day. The problem is, everyone forgets to do that everyday. Its super messy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even I do forget to do it at times. I entered office at 9.30 today and logged my attendance at 10.20, when a reminder popped up on my phone. Technically I was half an hour early to work, but I’m gonna suffer a 20 minutes delay mark in my performance sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, to get over this, I have decided to hack and automate the attendance module. like a boss&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the attendance module is a form, with three key input fields: 1) Username, 2) Password, and the 3) IN button. Employees have to fill up their assigned username and password, then punch the IN button to login their attendance for the day with date and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty easy to automate this process, at a trigger I can choose. What I can do is, simply use mechanize ( http://wwwsearch.sourceforge.net/mechanize/ ) to automate the form. That simple, yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trigger can be anything. Maybe a time frame or as soon as I turn my computer on from 9am to 12pm on week days. Or maybe when I check in into my office using the Swarm app. I never forget to check in on 4sq/Swarm!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I won’t be automating the Attendance Module. The attendance is a way I push myself to work early everyday, giving me some extra time to brainstorm or even prepare a list of things I need to get done that day. Cheerio.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Raj</name></author><category term="python" /><category term="automation" /><summary type="html">This place I work has an online portal where every employee must login with their user credentials and log their attendance for the day. The problem is, everyone forgets to do that everyday. Its super messy!</summary></entry></feed>